Mary Van Nes: Correspondence from Germany
Yale University Music Library
Mary Van Nes: Correspondence from Germany
1931-1933
Misc. Ms. 291
Yale University Music Library
0.5
(1 box)
Letters by the American pianist Mary Van Nes concerning her experience as a student of Arthur Schnabel in Germany
Van Nes, Mary
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to researchers by appointment. There are no restricted materials in the collection. Please contact the Special Collections staff to schedule an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was established in the Music Library of Yale University by Mary Van Nes in 1967.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Scope and Contents
Mary Van Nes's correspondence from Germany detailed her experiences in Berlin as a student of Artur Schnabel from 1931 to 1934. Upon receiving the letters, her mother edited and transcribed them into 11 notebooks. This collection includes notebooks 1-5 and 8-11; the collection lacks notebooks 6-7 (April-August 1932).
Biographical / Historical
Mary Van Nes is an American pianist who studied with Arthur Schnabel from 1931 to 1934. In later years, she was active in Westchester County, New York as a performer and as the organizer of the concert series of the Hudson River Museum. According to the New York Times, she was still performing in 1995, at the age of 89.
Music -- Instruction and study -- Germany; Pianists -- Correspondence; Germany -- Social life and customs -- 1918-1933; Schnabel, Artur, 1882-1951; Van Nes, Mary
- Correspondence
  - Inventory (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Notebook 1, June 12, 1931-July 22, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notebook 2, July 26, 1931-September 23, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notebook 3, October 3, 1931-November 16, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notebook 4, November 10, 1931-February 3, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notebook 5, February 10, 1932-April 2, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notebook 8, August 5, 1932,-September 1, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notebook 9, September 3, 1932-October 9, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notebook 10, October 17, 1932-November 6, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Notebook 11, November 16, 1932-February 10, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence with James Tanis, Yale University Librarian, November, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)